you're a Zen master but you're also
connected to the integral school ken
wilber and this this idea of sort of
developmental lens looking at culture
and looking at consciousness through a
very to the sense of where it's going
and how it's developing so it's a very
interesting mix of the sort of the
timeless Zen and the developmental path
of consciousness and we're gonna work
I'm gonna open by asking you a little
bit about Jordan Peterson at the risk of
feeling that all over the content and
all of our channel is about Jordan
Pederson I think it's I think the reason
for that is because I think it's a
really interesting window into some of
the deeper topics that I'm really hoping
to to explore with you about masculine
and feminine and where we are culturally
because I think the phenomena of Jordan
Pederson and the reaction to him for me
at least there's something really
archetypal about where we are in our
culture and so I'd love to hear what you
know just what you made of this this
incredible kind of phenomena that's
erupting over the last kind of year or
so I was so excited to see Jordan
Peterson erupted onto the stage and I
know you had particularly part in that
there is a culture war that is in bright
precedence I mean we are in the middle
of a culture war there's a polarization
and Jordan Peterson is standing in the
middle as a lightning rod taking all the
projections from both sides he clearly
sees the postmodern ideology and it is
an ideology it's a system of beliefs and
values that will not lead us to the
promised land it is it is problematic it
leads us into a swamp with no exit
it is not sustainable he sees it very
clearly and in my opinion he sees that
from a modern perspective very brilliant
modern perspective he's and he has a
depth because of his understanding of
Carl Jung and his own work in psychology
the field of psychology that is deeper
than most people so people are drawn to
that depth he sees something much deeper
then other people are seeing right now
for me when I see him describing this
ideology of postmodern a Galit Aryan
relativism and describing it so
precisely and then I listen to Ken
Wilber describing the same disease there
are some interesting differences between
their two descriptions and there are
even more interesting similarities
Jordan Peterson has the depth of Jung's
perspective and Ken has that too he
studied Jung anointment but he has a
much bigger philosophical view that is a
little bit more evolved past into the
integral Brown but the two perspectives
are fascinating to me and both of them
are critical the antidote the medicine
for the the post modernity
I believe Ken sees and I'm not sure
Jordan Peterson does and Ken has a name
for this he calls it a perspective on
madness and it is madness there's no way
out are the culture war in our our
society Western postmodern society at
war with modern beliefs and traditional
beliefs
is the psychosis so this a perspectival
madness is kind of best summarized as
this idea there is no truth and yet that
is a truth that's part of it
that's the Vanille ISM the the
relativistic nil ISM which is saying
there is no absolute truth and that's an
absolute truth everything's relative and
that's absolutely true that's
crazy-making that's half of it the other
half of it is rampant narcissism if
there is no absolute if there is no
power greater than my ego what am I
going to worship as Ken points out there
are studies that show that I'm a member
of the Me Generation narcissistic
sixties the people today the Millennials
are two and a half times more
narcissistic than the me generation that
just breaks my heart open there's no way
out of that no way out and when I work
with the Millennials it breaks my heart
I feel such compassion first of all
everybody's lied to them everybody's
told them what they believe is the truth
and no one's told them the truth it's
really interesting that you're that
you're talking about compassion there
because I'd say there's two there's two
things firstly the difference I think
with with Ken Wilbur's attitude towards
what he calls the broken green and and
that this maps on to what Jordan
Peterson would describer sort of the
postmodern neo-marxist worldview is the
Ken seems to see it as a necessary stage
of development and I get the sense with
Jordan Peterson and he's so he rejects
it so much that he he doesn't see it as
a necessary stage at all he just sees it
as a complete wrong turn in society but
the other the other point is that
you mentioned compassion for the people
who are stuck in this this is where I
have where I have a difficulty with with
Jordan Peterson is that I don't feel
that compassion for from him a lot of
the time he attacks it so strongly that
I don't feel whereas I would like what I
would like to see a bit more from him as
this sense of these people are have been
misdirected they've been misguided and a
sense of sort of almost like fatherly
kind of concern for them as much as we
need to eradicate this kind of worldview
it's wrong it leads to the Gulag data
which is interesting maybe that's the
Zen compassion that you're bringing in
if it is partially Zen but it's
partially the second tier perspective
it's partially what lies beyond green
I'm not convinced that green is a bridge
to the next level of consciousness it
may be and just to interject here for
our audience who may not know what green
is what is is the level of consciousness
that evolved or emerged more fully
during the 60s and is characterized by
relativism by post-modernism all these
things it's actually bringing to the
table some really critical ingredients
whether Green is the end of an epoch or
a bridge to the next epoch is not clear
yet there are some developmental
theorists that say Green is not really a
stage of development at all it's a half
stage it's not clear it's not like
modernity post modernity is kind of
confused and not really impossible to
emerge as a full-blown stage of
development because it's self
contradictory because it's got inherent
contradictions in it there's no way out
of it it may be a dead end it may be the
end of this epic rather than the
beginning of the next one or the
transition to the next
but if it's the end that's a transition
to isn't it it's not clear
Robert Keegan is such a developmental
theorists he doesn't see this postmodern
as a stage of development
he seems that more as a symptom it's
just not clear yet we don't we won't
know for a while we won't know till
we're looking back from the other side
so we'll see so I'm right in the middle
between Wilber and Jordan Peterson hmm
because I had read Carl Jung's collected
works by the time I was 24 that the
Union perspective was really important
to me and then I stumbled into Zen nice
done stumbled into Ken it's probably a
really good time to just get a brief
potted history of your of your
background how did you how do you come
to be a Zen master with the integral
tradition
I was raised Roman Catholic a German
Roman Catholic in a small farming
community in the mountains of Colorado I
didn't fit in I had my first direct
experience of God edie or emptiness very
young and many more and when I went to
talk about them I was beaten by the
clergy the nuns they were particularly
mean so I very quickly learned to not
say anything but I wasn't very good at
it so I kept saying things I kept
conflicting so by the time I was 17 I
was very rebellious and deeply disturbed
I'm lucky to be alive
I'm lucky to have survived such pent-up
anger and frustration and in
stubbornness so I met a woman a teacher
one of my friends drugged me to meet
this woman and I knocked on her door we
had to be there at exactly 8 o'clock
drove two hours to get there and this
white-haired woman with fire in her eyes
opened the door and she said welcome no
one comes here by chance work guided by
the unconscious because the unconscious
knows so this was like putting it a key
like Jordan Peterson talks about putting
a key in a hidden lock and something
opens I had felt this before when I was
very young and I learned that trust in
the Lord because the Lord knows it's the
same walk different key but the same
lock something opened then to all of a
sudden this really confused seventeen
year old of us not alone there was a
whole group of of people that ste Chur
introduced me to that I began to read
with a voracious appetite Carl Jung Eric
Newman
Joseph Campbell DT Suzuki Krishnamurti
mariachi Elliott a Herman HESA Watts a
world opened and and I fell into it I
started meditating about the same time
and I there was a an image and a words
that came out of nowhere as if from the
top of the mountain I was worried about
what am I gonna do when I grow up and
all of a sudden these words boomed out
of nowhere rather than finding your
place in the world
first find yourself and there will be
your place Here I am a so-called master
of Zen a lineage older and Rinzai Zen
samurai Zen
how perfect is this and I had read
Jung's work by the time I was 24 I think
like you thinks I see the same things
you saw the movement of collective
shadows what I see happening right now
breaks my heart open hmm nobody else
sees what I see
Jordon Peterson smells it I suspect but
I doesn't sound like he sees it what do
you say I'd rather not say I have a
sense that what we are seeing is the
eruption of the shadow in a big cultural
way and a lot of that is due to a lot of
is facilitated by technology we have
technology that suddenly so now not
everything before was going through a
few different channels the broadcaster's
the the mainstream media and suddenly
we've democratized the media we've
democratized a lot of the information
and so what I see happening is that we
have all of these things that were kept
out of the behind closed doors or were
just we assumed we're not part of our
society anymore now erupting out of the
cracks between things
beginning to you I agree I think this is
just the beginning of we have no idea
what's coming I think we maybe have a
suspicion I don't think we do probably
but but that's my sense and that's where
I wonder whether what you're referring
to is that same sense that we're gonna
have to do some serious shadow work as a
culture over the next to survive to
survive yeah what you're pointing to and
what you're seeing with technology in
your position as being part of the media
for the first time in human history I
have access on my cell phone to the
great works of the greatest thinkers and
sages of all time right here
Google what did aristotle say about this
right here this has never happened
before we have the ability to to look on
YouTube for all these teachings and
these teachers never happened before if
we have no idea how this is gonna impact
consciousness and the unconscious
we just are in such a bold experiment
and it's going to be amazing what
happens and terrifying I suspect I can
hardly wait to see what it is do you
have an idea of time scales because
things seem to be accelerating very
quickly they are accelerating there is
no time from an absolute perspective and
from a relative perspective of course
there's this construct applause a very
persuasive illusion then it is a very
persistent illusion so is the south most
this ego is so persistent but it's not
real as ramana maharshi said the only
thing that's real is what is present and
deep dreamless sleep everything else is
an illusion and illusions can kill so
can culture wars you you use the word
culture war a couple of times now and I
think this is very interesting because
it seems quite clear that whatever was
sparked in the 60s the culture war that
kind of yes certainly was fueled by what
happened in the 60s seems now to me to
be getting bigger and bigger it's almost
like a fractal pattern that was
affecting a certain number of people in
the 60s has just got bigger and bigger
and bigger until it seems to be impact
in the whole of culture now you were
part of
you're a little bit older than me what
do you make of that do you think these
are exactly the same dynamics and if so
what lessons do you have from your
experience for how we should deal with
what's happening right now the image of
a lake comes to me in fact it's a lake
where I grew up and it was pristine
water when I grew up and now with the
global warming and with the amount of
nitrates that are in the ground and have
seeped into the groundwater the the
whole lake has died with a green algae
that has spread across the lake and
killed all life the postmodern culture
is spreading just like your fractals
taking over from the modern culture but
my view is of what happens if it's so
dysfunctional that it kills the pristine
lake it's not clear what's gonna happen
yet I see the danger of that happening
the medicine for the illnesses of the
post-modern a Galit Aryan relativism
which is the ideology that's prominent
now in this postmodern culture two
medicines one is shadow work two is
understanding the evolution of
consciousness because that is the next
view that negates the blind spots of the
pluralism you must see that pluralism is
not the answer it's not the end it's not
those who are pluralistic or enlightened
that's just not true that's a lie it's
just another step it's a bigger truth
than modernity but it's not the truth
the truth is the whole thing the whole
so this is those two things shadow work
and evolution you you mentioned shadow
work and that was pretty much the main
topic of my first interview with Jordan
Pederson he was the first person I'd
ever heard speak about it in a way that
really resonated with me in the way
because I I've done her personal growth
work probably over 12 years or so and a
lot of was was built around the shadow
like integrating different parts of of
ourselves and he was the first person
I'd heard speak to that in such a
compelling way and you you you just sort
of hinted that this is the essential
work I have the same the same feeling
that the way through that sort of chaos
of that I think's coming and I think we
all recognize is coming has to involve
us all doing that really essential in a
work of shadow integration what does
that look like and how how would you
describe the importance of that for
individuals and I guess a whole society
that's a really big question and I trust
each on stress it looks like being
really fucking uncomfortable and it's
forbidden to be uncomfortable and post
modernity you have to be nice
you can't give anybody any feedback you
can't tell the truth you have to lie you
have to avoid negative feelings at all
costs those all kill any real shadow
work you have to be willing not only to
dive into the darkest darkness but be
really uncomfortable and see all the
hideous aspects of yourself that's the
simple answer
that also sounds very difficult to
achieve in an English society you ought
to try it the German society I was just
in Germany or an American mush yeah but
that that what I what I love about that
and also the way you delivered it was
that for me it's real spirituality yes
anything else this whole love and light
transcendence can I call it bullshit
let's call it bullshit yeah let's call
it bullshit is I it just it just really
irritates me just this whole sort of
sense of that spirituality is just here
up rather than here down because all of
the valuable work that I've done has
been digging in the dirt really going
into it and that people don't want to do
is digging in the shit yeah not the dirt
you got to go deeper of course people
don't want to do it the the addiction
and post modernity seems to be wanting
to feel good you know you can't do the
deeper work if you're limited to feeling
good that there was a Buddhist teacher
blame the baby boomers for that no we
can't blame anybody we have to take
responsibility
blaming world health our part of the
problem we must take responsibility so
in post modernity I just did some
beautiful work in a shadow webinar that
I I just finished collective shadows
most interesting subject part two of a
three part series on shadows the the the
rescuer the victim and the perpetrator
this is an endless cycle in post
modernity they are identified with the
rescuer which is really deep down
it's the savior the archetype of the
savior now how deep are those roots in
Christian soil the victim is the
sacrificial lamb who must be sacrificed
and stay sacrificed no redemption and
the perpetrator becomes the scapegoat
that in the Talmud the Old Testament was
loaded up with the sins of the people
and chased into the desert to die the
scapegoat the one that carried the
burdens which meant we had to we had to
account for our sins on the Day of
Atonement Yom Kippur my favorite holiday
so we must add something to this trilogy
to make it whole and complete and what
we had and integrals in is the witness
who sees everything the whole dynamics
the rescuer keeps the victim stuck in
perpetual victimhood
unable to take responsibility and
projects their own responsibility blames
the scapegoat what happened in Germany
was Hitler needed a scapegoat oh my what
a perfect match what a playing out of
these archetypal forces in the most
hideous way this is just one example you
know I don't blame the Germans because
genocides have never ended
there are genocides happening right now
that are equally hideous and until we
get in touch with the hideous beast that
breathes in the shadowy depths of
own haunted soul individually and stop
blaming others for what is part of us
they will continue and the weapons are
getting much bigger and more deadly as
Einstein said I don't know what weapons
the third world war will be fought with
who knows what they have in the in the
warehouses he said I do know what
weapons the fourth world war will be
fought with sticks and stones so another
lens that we've looked at or will use to
look at a lot of the cultural and the
social dynamics that are going on at the
moment is is gender masculine and
feminine and in some sense you can look
at what's going on now is kind of this
dysfunctional relationship between men
and women that's now being that sort of
on the biggest cultural stage and I have
a just asked what you what you make of
that do you think that that's quite a
useful frame to look at the world
absolutely it is a huge part of life
masculine and feminine is everywhere you
look if I look through a union lens then
the Animus and the anima the
relationship with the opposite sex
parent is where your relationship with
your soul begins it's who you will marry
that's a continuation that vector
continues and it becomes so important to
understand and to get to the roots of
that little child that inevitably gets
wounded and masculine and feminine for
me the the confusion I would sort of
simplify as we've confused equality with
equivalents so explain that for me
please so we've confused equality with
same
yes that in our drive to equality to
women being able to choose their
destinies for probably the first time
since the its in since the sixties and
sharing spaces with men what I think
we've confused is the complementarity of
masculine and feminine and men and women
with equality with a sameness an
assumption of sameness and my sense from
teaching men's work and and increasingly
doing polarity work is that the way out
is to really ground ourselves in our
inner as men in our masculine to then be
able to meet the in a feminine which we
also have as men and the outer feminine
as well and it's kind of it's it's the
the paradox of the sacred marriage of
masculine feminine but that can only
happen if we really go into our own
biological reality so I completely agree
with what you see what you said and I
want to add another confusing
complication to that confusion that you
articulated there are really two things
going on that are merged together like
trauma one is developmental we're moving
from modernity to postmodernity to
something that will work whatever it is
post modernity is not working it's stuck
it's not sustainable so that's one thing
that's going on then we have this battle
between masculine and feminine you know
it's like an argument that needs to be a
marriage a sacred marriage these two
things are confusing enough in
themselves but when we merge them into
one mess and try to solve the one mess
it's a far bigger problem than can be
solved it's a wicked problem that
no solution and we're stuck there so
what you're pointing to is just half of
it there's another half that is equally
problematic and the combination and
there's probably more confusion that I'm
not seeing but this makes it unsolvable
with this approach we must separate that
differentiate these two things and and
work on them independently and you've
got one of them very clearly so let's
talk about that one I understand as well
that you were part of some of the early
explorations of what you might call the
the men's movement yes could you talk
about that Oh be careful how much time
do you have I was part of an
organization called the mankind project
something happened after I became very
active in the mankind project I had to
go attend to my mother who was ill and
when I came back there was a complete
transition this thing called
multiculturalism had infiltrated the
ranks and all of a sudden there were
these these men teaching us that we were
prejudiced and they neglected to mention
the fact that they were prejudiced as
well but we could smell it you know what
they were prejudiced against prejudice
everybody's with theirs and it stunk
still does that's another one of the the
performative contradictions of post
modernity particularly the ideology of
postmodern a Galit Arian pluralism they
say one thing with their mouths and say
another thing with their
actions with their mouths are saying I'm
not prejudiced with their actions are
saying I'm prejudiced against prejudiced
this is a problem this is a problem it
has no integrity it doesn't speak the
same truth there is a shadow here
that's unspoken but felt this prejudice
not a good thing to be protested against
like it absolutely is of course but you
need to own the fact that you're
prejudiced and then it's not a problem
if you pretend you're not prejudiced it
stinks
that's a performative contradiction
you're lying if you say I and I am
prejudiced against prejudiced aren't you
of course who wouldn't be so telling
that truth and not lying about it not
pretending to be greater than somebody
while pretending to be equal is where we
need to go we need to tell the truth the
whole truth and nothing but the truth we
need the whole truth rather than just
the perfect truth that will make us a
beer to be enlightened and so-called
equal perfectly equal is there such a
thing as perfect equality I've never
experienced it it's just an idea and
when I try to teat treat people as
though everybody's equal it's such a
disservice cuz I can't I can't treat
them for who they are I can't treat them
with respect respect for who they are
and all their their their individuality
so this is a interesting it's a moral
dilemma
hmm and moral dilemmas lie at the core
of culture wars this is something that
Jordan Peterson says about you don't
treat everyone with respect otherwise it
devalues the currency there's something
different
treating people with common decency is
one thing treating everyone you meet
with respect is something different
because respect is earned I have a
little semantic difference in the way I
would describe that I get the spirit of
what he's saying and I agree with the
spirit but I do go out of my way to
respect everyone this is a mark of what
I would call awakened mind respect for
everyone the difference what must be
earned is not respect it's trust this
must be earned and we're saying the same
thing different words and would you say
that you're respecting the person as
they appear you were respecting the
person who they could become I look at
you and I see Buddha see your arse eyes
just Sparkle you just became Buddha this
is awakened mind that light that just
sparkled in your eyes is what I see when
I look in your eyes I see all the shit -
mm-hmm
but that's what I respect is the Buddha
or Christos same thing
what is the medicine for an addiction
like an addiction to ourselves like
cultural narcissism when a a the
founders of a a who were deeply
influenced by Carl Jung Jung gave them a
secret ingredient to combat addiction
prior to a a alcoholism was incurable
the greatest medical mind said there is
no cure for alcoholism if you were an
alcoholic you were written off no
treatment possible what they got from
um-- the
part of a a Alcoholics Anonymous was a
realignment was something some power
that's greater than ourselves this is
the medicine for narcissism this is a
necessary ingredient
if we can't awaken something more sacred
than ourselves and the devotion do it
we're not going to survive what I'm also
sort of feeling from you as well it's
something that I recognize in true
spirituality which is this level of
intensity it's I mean in a way that's
what I understand even meditation it's
like can you be here now can it be
really really here
and can you be really here with all of
you right now that for me is the essence
of all the spiritual work that I've done
is can you access that level of
intensity and that means accessing all
of the parts of yourself the anger that
yeah the everything at the same time the
whole yeah enchilada yeah so there you
go sparkling again mmm so I've got bad
news for ya if you spot it you've got it
you've got no choice but to become the
Buddha that you already are don't matter
what and you have that intensity never
turn away those were things that happen
oh there's much worse things tap
there's fate much worse than death
machine you are a Zen master and there
are no masters as there there are no
masters but I've always wanted to do
this
is that great that's the wrong answer if
you flood the sparkle in your eye has
already answered the correct answer for
the coatt yeah
don't confuse the audience this is one
hand clapping this is one hand clapping
what is not one hand clapping and can
you see this deep truth in all things
I've seen thank you very much absolute
pleasure any time
you